A Guide to the Henry Thweatt Owen Papers, 1822-1929
Library of Virginia
- Letters, 1856-1924
  - 24 May 1880, 3 p.; W. F. Clark, Keysville, Virginia, to Captain Owen, concerning the composition of Pickett's Division in the Battle of Gettysburg and of his own regiment, 56th. (Folder 3)
  - 17 September 1880, 1 p.; Edmund R. Cocke, Oakland, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, with regard to the casualties in his company at the Battle of Gettysburg. (Folder 3)
  - 8 October 1880, 1 p.; "Friends," Richmond, Virginia, to Captain Owen, complimenting him on his "defence of Manhood" and remitting his fine of twenty dollars. (Folder 3)
  - 2 February 1881, 3 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to his daughter "Mamee" Owen, discussing her letter to him and sending his regards to his family. (Folder 3)
  - 17 March 1881, 1 p.; The Times, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, accepting his Gettysburg manuscript for publication and returning "the other." (Folder 3)
  - 20 July 1881, Printed broadsude, 1 p.; H. H. Dyson, Richmond, Virginia, "To the Republicans of Virginia," urging their support of the Readjuster party in Virginis. (Folder 3)
  - 4 October 1881, 5 p.; Charles Pickett, Norfolk, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, giving his account of the attack by Pickett's division at Malvern Hill. (Folder 3)
  - 20 November 1881, 6 p.; George H. Southall, Lynchburg, Virginia, to H. H. Dyson, glorying in the Readjuster victory at the polls (even with poetry) and asking for a job. (Folder 3)
  - 17 December 1881, 4 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to his wife [Harriet Owen], discussing his heavy workload in the Second Auditor's Office and prospective changes among the staff. (Folder 3)
  - 1881, 3 p.; [Henry T. Owen?], Richmond, Virginia, to "Dear Sir," supporting the Readjuster program and urging the election of John E. Massey as Governor. (Folder 3)
  - 21 February 1882, 3 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "C. H. Bliss, N. H. Champlin, A. W. Harris, and others," declining appointment to the post of First Clerk in the Second Auditor's Office and giving his reasons in detail. Draft copy. (Folder 3)
  - 23 February 1882, 3 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "C. H. Bliss, N. H. Champlin, A. W. Harris, and others," declining appointment to the post of First Clerk in the Second Auditor's Office and giving his reasons in detail. Sent copy[?]. (Folder 3)
  - 3 September 1882, 1 p.; C. Linkenhoker, Richmond, Virginia, to Captain [Henry T. Owen], regretting that Owen will not be returning to Richmond "but, such is politics." (Folder 3)
  - 16 November 1882, 5 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Honorable John E. Massey, offering his encouragement upon hearing of Massey's decision to contest the election of his opponent to his seat in Congress, and giving a detailed account of an election fraud in his precinct. (Folder 3)
  - 22 November 1882, 2 p.; C. Linkenhoker, Richmond, Virginia, to Captain [Henry T. Owen], commenting upon John S. Wise's election as Governor. (Folder 3)
  - 22 November 1882, 4 p.; F. G. Morrison, Henrico County, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia, commenting on the election, discussing the clerks in the Second Auditor's Office, and giving personal news. (Folder 3)
  - 25 November 1882, 4 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, to Colonel Frank G. Ruffin, expressing his disappointment that his private letter to John E. Massey (letter dated 16 November 1882 above) was published in the newspaper, outlining the difficulties it put him in, and commenting on politics generally. (Folder 3)
  - 12 November 1883, 1 p.; Corbin M. Reynolds, Carolina P. O., Botetourt County, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, seeking a government job for Colonel Frank G. Ruffin, and commenting on Mahone's defeat. (Folder 3)
  - 22 November 1883, 6 p.; Henry T. Owen, Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Judge F. N. Watkins, asking him to use his influence to procure a post for Colonel Frank G. Ruffin, outlining Ruffin's accomplishments, and in a humorous postscript complaining about Ruffin's "abominable" handwriting. (Folder 3)
  - 26 November 1883, 4 p.; Franks G. Ruffin, Richmond, Virginia, to "My friend" [Henry T. Owen?], thanking him for his efforts in his behalf, discussing political fortunes, and alluding to his handwriting. (Folder 3)
  - 14 December 1883, 2 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Green Bay [Prince Edward County], Virginia, to Colonel [Frank G.] Ruffin, regarding the possible support of Senator Williams for Owen for a clerk's position, and his desire to remain free of obligation to Williams, considering his former treachery. (Folder 3)
  - 29 December 1883, 1 p.; Frank G. Ruffin, Danville, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia, with regard to Ruffin's assumption of the office of Auditor after the first of the year. (Folder 3)
  - 11 January 1884, 4 p.; William Smith, Hot Springs, Arkansas, to Captain Henry T. Owen, concerning Virginia politics and the high prices in Hot Springs. (Folder 4)
  - 4 March 1884, 3 p.; [Henry T. Owen?], Richmond, Virginia, to "Editor of the State," concerning race relations and the desire of the former slaves to repeal the law against mixed marriages (Folder 4)
  - 17 October 1884, 2 p.; Stephen Stanley, Attleboro Falls, Massachusetts, to Henry T. Owen, concerning his efforts to locate Captain Frank R. Josselyn of the 11th Massachusetts Regiment, whom Owen had befriended after the Battle of Gettysburg (see letter dated 18 July 1863 above). (Folder 4)
  - 2 January 1885, 1 p.; Stephen Stanley, Attleboro Falls, Massachusetts, to Henry T. Owen, concerning Josselyn and enclosing a letter. (Folder 4)
  - Enclosure, n.d., 3 p.; George T. Bosson to Stephen Stanley, thanking him for the information about his late brother-in-law, Captain Frank R. Josselyn, who died of illness contracted while a prisoner. (Folder 4)
  - 20 January 1885, 3 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to George C. Cabell, recommending W. Chase Morton for the position of Revenue Collector for the Second District of Virginia. (Folder 4)
  - 28 February 1885, 3 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Richmond, Virginia, to "Mrs. Weiss," correcting two errors in her newspaper article on the battle between the Merrimac and the Monitor. (Folder 4)
  - 14 May 1885, 2 p.; P. W. McKinney, Farmville, Virginia, to Captain [Henry T. Owen], regarding his efforts to get Mrs. Owen appointed postmistress at Green Bay. (Folder 4)
  - 7 December 1885, 1 p.; Appointment of Harriet A. Owen as Postmaster at Green Bay, Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 4)
  - 6 May 1886, 3 p.; George T. Bosson, Boston, Massachusetts, to Henry T. Owen, concerning Owen's kindness toward his late brother-in-law, Captain Frank R. Josselyn, and the plan of Bosson and his wife to travel to Richmond to meet him. (Folder 4)
  - 21 May 1886, 1 p.; J. C. Ropes, Boston, Massachusetts, to Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, in regard to an article on the war. (Folder 4)
  - 25 May 1886, 6 p.; L. Jeannette Bosson (wife of George T. Bosson), Boston, Massachusetts, to Captain [Henry T.] Owen, thanking him for his hospitality and inviting him to visit them. (Folder 4)
  - 3 June 1886, 2 p.; B. W. Currier, Boston, Massachusetts, to Captain Henry T. Owen, explaining that Frank Josselyn was his closest friend and inviting Owen to come to Boston. (Folder 4)
  - 27 June 1886, 4 p.; Mrs. George T. Bosson, Allston, Massachusetts, to Captain [Henry T.] Owen, thanking him for his letter and reminiscing abut her visit to Richmond. (Folder 4)
  - 14 July 1886, 4 p.; B. F. Williams, Gilberton, Pennsylvania, to Captain Henry T. Owen, asking his help in preventing some land in Lunenburg County from being sold for delinquent taxes. (Folder 4)
  - 30 July 1886, 4 p.; Mrs. George T. Bosson, Boston, Massachusetts, to Captain [Henry T.] Owen, forwarding photographs of her children and commenting on a meeting with William Mahone. (Folder 4)
  - 5 August 1886, 8 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to Mrs. [George T.] Bosson, thanking her for the photographs of her three children, discussing politics, and expressing his admiration for New England. (Folder 4)
  - 1 April 1887, 5 p.; Maggie J. Baker, Berkeley County, West Virginia, to Mr. [Henry T.] Owen, informing him, in response to his letter addressed to the postmaster, that hers was the house in which he had breakfast with his prisoner, Frank R. Josselyn. (Folder 4)
  - 24 June 1887, Fragment, 2 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Richmond, Virginia, to Captain J. C. Griffin, concerning the use of dogs in pursuing runaway slaves, and beginning a long story about a slave chasing dog named Boston who lived near Burkeville before the war. (Folder 4)
  - 20 July 1887, 4 p.; Robert A. Bright, Williamsburg, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, regarding Pickett's Division at Gettysburg and his role as a message bearer for Pickett. (Folder 4)
  - Circular letter, 25 November 1887, 2 p.; Jonas Kelly, Richmond, Virginia, to Members of the General Assembly, Richmond, Virginia, announcing his candidacy for the office of Superintendent of the State Prison, and describing errors in the current Superintendent's report. (Folder 4)
  - 25 February 1888, 1 p.; B. Hilton Owen, Clover Depot, Virginia, to "Pa" [Henry T. Owen], describing his work, a debate he engaged in, and the fight that followed. (Folder 4)
  - 9 January 1890, 2 p.; B. F. Williams, Mahanox City, Pennsylvania, to Captain Henry T. Owen, informing him that a Pennsylvania investor may visit Owen to be shown some land owned by Williams and Owen for possible purchase for its mineral content. (Folder 4)
  - 14 November 1890, 1 p.; B. T. Medley to "Cousin Henry" T. Owen, sending him an undated note, written on the same sheet (Henry T. Owen to D. F. Medley) during a class when they were both in grammer school, on family matters. (Folder 4)
  - 24 March 1896, 1 p.; James Mann, Nottoway Court House, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, informing him that he has been elected an honorary member of the Pickett-Stuart Camp of Confederate Veterans, and must prepare a eulogy on some member of the regiment to be delivered at the April meeting of the Camp. (Folder 4)
  - 27 March 1896, 1 p.; James Mann, Nottoway Court House, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, explaining the purpose of the eulogy and refusing to excuse him from the task. (Folder 4)
  - 11 February 1897, 1 p.; John R. Taylor, Hanover Court House, Virginia, to Henry T. Owen, describing the Hanover County record books in his possession and saying that he did not find the Owen family name in the index. (Folder 4)
  - 28 March 1897, 1 p.; Stith Bolling, Petersburg, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, concerning subscriptions to a history of the 9th Virginia Regiment, and noting that the roll of Company G may contain errors. (Folder 4)
  - 11 August 1897, 1 p.; Moses D. Hoge, Richmond, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, concerning Owen's efforts to obtain information on Judah P. Benjamin for a friend's memoir. (Folder 4)
  - 7 January 1898, 2 p.; P. W. McKinney, Farmville, Virginia, to Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, asking him to investigate the Mutual Guarantee Building and Loan Association of Richmond to find if McKinney's investment in five or six shares of its stock is a safe one. (Folder 4)
  - October 1898, 2 p.; Lyon G. Gardiner, [Williamsburg, Virginia], to [Henry T. Owen], a printed advertisement for the William and Mary College Quarterly Historical Magazine, with a tearsheet of the contents of volume seven, number two, and a handwritten note asking Owen to subscribe. (Folder 4)
  - 20 December 1898, 1 p.; W. G. Stanard, Richmond, Virginia, to Captain Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, informing him of his election as a member of the Virginia Historical Society. (Folder 4)
  - 21 March 1900, 3 p.; B. T. Medley, Meherrin, Virginia, to "Cousin Henry" [T. Owen], Richmond, Virginia, asking him to keep the old family Bible, and discussing family matters. Page two is missing. Includes envelope. (Folder 4)
  - 16 July 1901, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to Kenneth C. Johnson (Owen's grandson), Bruceville, Virginia, on family matters and describing a kitten given to Mrs. Owen. (Folder 4)
  - 29 March 1902, 5 p.; [Henry T. Owen], Richmond, Virginia, to Colonel R. E. Withers, Wytheville, Virginia, concerning the events leading up to his court martial in September 1861, apparently for insubordination with regard to his failing to obey orders concerning some sickness in his company. This letter is incomplete. (Folder 4)
  - 7 July 1902, 1 p.; N. R. Bowman, Lynchburg, Virginia, to "Cousin" Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, thanking him for sending genealogical information concerning his family. (Folder 4)
  - 22 Septembr 1908, 2 p.; Edward R. Baird, Occupacia, Virginia, to [Henry T. Owen], concerning a meeting of former officers held in 1894 to vindicate the conduct of General Pickett at Gettysburg and in regard to a newspaper article on the subject. (Folder 4)
  - 12 November 1913, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "My dear daughter," concerning his alleged resemblance to General Grant, the cold weather, and family matters. (Folder 4)
  - 12 March 1918, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "Mamie" (his daughter), thanking her for the letters and candy, and describing his present sickness. (Folder 4)
  - 29 January 1919, 2 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "Mamie" (his daughter), regarding another box of candy, Mr. Styll's narrow escape from a bridge accident, and Owen's enthusiasm for Billy Sunday. (Folder 4)
  - 23 June 1920, 12 p.; Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to "Mich" (his son), discussing current events foretold by the prophets of the Bible, and commenting on the admirable life of Queen Victoria. (Folder 4)
  - Envelope, 8 March 1924, H. C. Stuart, Elk Garden, Virginia, to Mrs. Constance T. Watson, Richmond, Virginia. (Folder 4)
- Land Records, 1894-1928
  - Letter, 16 March 1894, 2 p.; Executive Committee, Newport News, Hampton, and Old Point Development Company, Richmond, Virginia, to Mr. E. O. Whiteside, informing him that he has been assigned a lot in exchange for his stock, pursuant to a resolution adopted by the stockholders for closing up the Company. On the reverse is a handwritten note, dated 6 September 1900, from L. T. Christian describing the dissolution of the Company. (Folder 5)
  - Joseph Thompson, abstract of title to 200 acres of land in Prince Edward County, Virginia, belonging to G. C. Womack. 21 April 1909, 4 p. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 24 July 1909, 2 p.; George C. Womack and Martin Womack, his wife, of Prince Edward County, Virginia, to E. O. Whiteside and Henry Whiteside of Charlotte County, Virginia, for 131 acres in Prince Edward County. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 25 August 1914, Purcell Cox, of Prince Edward County, Virginia, to Julius Lash of Meherrin, Virginia, for one acre in Prince Edward County. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - unrecorded, 18 June 1917, 2 p.; Virso Investment Corporation of Virginia, to Mary G. Whiteside, for one lot in Virso, Virginia. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 18 June 1917, 4 p.; Purcell Cox, Lee Cox, and his wife Annie Cox, to E. O. Whiteside, for one third acre in Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 26 November 1917, 1 p.; Purcell Cox to E. O. Whiteside, his interest in the estate of his father, Mat Cox, being two parcels of land in Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 5)
  - Deed of trust - recorded, 30 November 1920, D. J. Thompson, of Prince Edward County, Virginia, to E. O. Whiteside, of Lunenburg County, Virginia, for 90 acres in Prince Edward County. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 8 April 1921, 4 p.; Julius Lash and Susan A. Lash, his wife, to E. O. Whiteside, for four-tenths of an acre in Prince Edward County, Virginia. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 15 February 1921, 3 p.; Robert K. Brock to E. O. Whiteside, for seven and a half acres in Prince Edward County, Virginia, and receipt for clerk's fees. (Folder 5)
  - W. J. Lyle, Keysville, Virginia, copy of advertisement of sale by auction of 90 acres in Prince Edward County, Virginia, to be held 17 October 1928., 1 p. (Folder 5)
  - W. J. Lyle to F. L. Blanton, Farmville, Virginia, 14 December 1928, 1 p.; Settlement of his trustee's account. (Folder 5)
  - Deed - recorded, 14 March 1929, 3 p.; W. J. Lyle, Charlotte County, Virginia, to Henry Whiteside, for 90 acres in Prince Edward County. (Folder 5)
- Military Papers, 6 November 1862-8 August 1864, 83 items (Folder 6)
  Includes letters, orders, and receipts of a military nature, especially concerning Union prisoners assembled for exchange at City Point.
- Lists of Casualties and Units at Gettysburg n.d., 21 items (Folder 7)
  Includes estimates of Union strength, company rosters, and lists of officers killed and wounded in Pickett's Charge.
- Diary, 10 February-10 July 1863, 12 p. (Folder 8)
  This diary, written by Henry T. Owen, is titled "Notes from a Diary kept during the war of the Rebellion" and traces his regiment's movements from Petersburg through the retreat from Gettysburg.
- Reminiscences
  - "Reminiscences of the War," by Captain Henry T. Owen, n.d., 7 p. (Folder 9)
  - "Pickett's Division" [Gettysburg Campaign], n.d., 17 p. (Folder 9)
  - "Battle of South Mountain," n.d., 16 p. (Folder 9)
  - Letter, 27 January 1878, 8 p.; Henry T. Owen, Green Bay, Virginia, to Colonel H. A. Carrington, giving a marvelously detailed account of his participation in Pickett's Charge and the aftermath. (Folder 9)
- Drafts of Articles
  - "The Battle of Dranesville," by Henry T. Owen with cover letter, Henry T. Owen, Richmond, Virginia, to Editor of Times, submitting the article, 25 August 1885, 50 p. (Folder 10)
  - "Pickett's Division," n.d., 7 p.; By Henry T. Owen, written for the South-Side Sentinel (Folder 10)
  - Notes for the "Battle of Dranesville," n.d., 7 p. (Folder 10)
  - Description of parade of 18th Virginia Regiment in Richmond, Virginia, on 26 May 1861, n.d., 1 p. (Folder 10)
  - Description of sermon of Dr. D. L. Moody, n.d., 1 p. (Folder 10)
  - Draft of article on the role of Pickett's Division in the Battle of Gettysburg, n.d., 12 p. (Folder 10)
  - Drafts of biographical sketch of Chatham Roberdeau Wheat, n.d., 14 p. (Folder 10)
  - Account of a sermon preached by the Second Adventist William T. Thurman in 1875, n.d., 7 p. (Folder 10)
  - "Rambling around Richmond," n.d., 8 p.; Concerning changes in the city. Includes several drafts. (Folder 10)
  - Fragment of article asserting that the Southern politicians who stirred up the rebellion were demogogues who abandoned the soldier to his fate once the action got hot, n.d., 5 p. (Folder 10)
  - Notes on the Battle of Seven Pines, n.d, 10 p. (Folder 10)
  - Macaulay's opinion of the U. S. Government (fragment), 1857, 2 p. (Folder 10)
  - Speeches of Honorable John F. Shafroth, House of Representatives, 1 and 7 February 1900, 16 p. (Folder 10)
- Poetry
  - "The Captain strode from fore to aft," n.d., 1 p. (Folder 11)
  - "At the ford of the river we held the foe back," n.d., 1 p. (Folder 11)
  - "As on they rushed into the strife," n.d., 1 p. (Folder 11)
  - "Was there no friend on whom depend," n.d., 1 p. (Folder 11)
- Newspaper - The Charlotte Gazette,15 May 1884, 4 p. (Folder 12)
- Photographs
  - Captain H. T. Owen (New York Art Gallery, Richmond, Virginia), ca. 1861, Tinted albumen print, 6-1/2 x 4-1/4 in. (Folder 13)
  - H. T. Owen (Richmond Photo Company, Richmond, Virginia), n.d., Albumen print, 7-1/2 x 5 in. (Folder 13)
  - H. T. Owen (New York Art Gallery, Richmond, Virginia), n.d., Albumen print, 6-1/2 x 4-1/4 in. (Folder 13)
  - H. T. Owen, "nearly ninety," ca. 1920, Silver print, 5 x 3-1/2 in. (Folder 13)
- James Whiteside Papers, 1863-1893
  - James Whiteside, discharge from 46th Regiment of Pennsylvania Militia, 18 August 1863, 2 p. (Folder 14)
  - John C. Hamlett, Sr., Charlotte County, Virginia, survey and plat of 924 acres in Charlotte County, Virginia, 16 December 1870, 4 p. (Folder 14)
  - Receipt 9 January 1871, 2 p.; John C. Hamlett, Sr., to Henry Whiteside, Clearfield County, Pennsylvania, receipt for first installment on land sold by Hamlett to Whiteside. (Folder 14)
  - Receipt for taxes, 1873, 1 p.; Andrew B. Paris (per Cauthorn) to Henry Whiteside (Folder 14)
  - James Whiteside, Insurance Policy, Virginia Fire and Marine Insurance Company, Richmond, 14 November 1884, 2 p. (Folder 14)
  - James Whiteside, in account with Jeffress and Company, Keysville, Virginia, 9 January 1893, 4 p. (Folder 14)
- Plat Books, 1728-1783 and ca. 1880-ca. 1900, 2 volumes
  Henry T. Owen's compilation of surveys and plats of patents and grants issued for Prince Edward County, Virginia. First volume, 1728-1783, is indexed with finished plats and surveys; second volume, ca. 1800-ca. 1900, contains rough drafts of plats and notes about land purchases by people with various surnames, including Owen.
- Maps
  - Railroad map of United States with emphasis on distances between San Francisco and Richmond, before 1889, Colored, 17 x 44-1/2 in.
  - Newport News, Hampton, and Old Point Development Company, Braxton, Chandler, and Marye, Civil Engineers, 1891, 28 x 24-1/2 in.
  - Plats, surveys, and notes concerning early settlers in Prince Edward County, Virginia, Colored, sizes vary, 58 items.
  - Plats and maps of property in and near the town of Virso, Prince Edward and Lunenburg Counties, Virginia, ca. 1902-ca. 1924, Sizes vary, 76 items.
  - Map of the Battle Field of Gettysburg, First Day's Battle, Office of the Chief of Engineers, United States Army, 1876, Colored, 39 x 31 in.
- Broadsides
  - "To the Survivors of Pickett's Division," 15 December 1887, 11 x 8-1/2 in.
  - "Garnett's Brigade," n.d., 30 x 16 in.
- Second Auditor's Office, 5 items
  Lists of coupon issued under Acts of 1871, 1879, and 1892, paid into the Second Auditor's Office by warrant on the Treasurers.